A Finding Aid to the Joan Semmel Papers, 1949-2013, bulk circa 1960s-2013, in the Archives of American Art AAA.semmjoan
Archives of American Art
Joan Semmel papers
bulk 1960-2013
1949-2013
AAA.semmjoan
Archives of American Art
5.9 Linear feet
The papers of painter Joan Semmel measure 5.9 linear feet and are dated 1949-2013, bulk circa 1960s-2013. The papers reflect her career and activities as a painter, writer, feminist and educator through biographical materials, correspondence, interviews, writings, project files, teaching files, printed material, and photographic materials.
Semmel, Joan
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 8 seres:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1949-2013 (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1973-2013 (Boxes 1-2; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Interviews, circa 1970s-1986 (Box 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1970s-2009 (Box 3; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 5: Project Files, 1972-2000 (Box 3; 3 folders)
Series 6: Teaching Files, 1970s-2000 (Box 3; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Material, circa 1960s-2013 (Boxes 4-6, OV 8; 2.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographic Materials, circa 1965-2013 (Boxes 6-7; 0.6 linear feet)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Joan Semmel in 2014.
Biographical/Historical note
Joan Semmel (1932- ), a figurative painter in New York, NY and Easthampton, NY, is known for erotic themes and bringing a feminist sensibility to paintings of the female body. She taught painting at Mason Gross School of the Arts, Rutgers University for twenty years.
Born in New York City in 1932, Joan Semmel studied Cooper Union (diploma, 1952), the Art Students League of New York (1958-1959), and Pratt Institute (BFA, 1963; MFA, 1972). Semmel moved to Spain in 1963 and exhibited her abstract expressionist work in galleries and museums.
Upon returning to New York in 1970, Semmel enrolled in Pratt Institute's MFA program and became engaged by the feminist movement. One of the original Guerrilla Girls, she was involved with several art groups devoted to gender equality in the art world. Semmel organized exhibitions about women artists and spent years researching a book about women's erotic art. At the same time, her style shifted to figurative painting and she began working in series that explored the female body, desire and aging. Each series of 10-30 paintings, produced over several years, was consistent in style and theme, among them: First and Second Erotic Series, Self Images, Portraits, Figure in Landscape, Gymnasium, Locker Room, Overlays, and Mannequins.
Prior to her long association with Rutgers University as a tenured Professor of Painting, Semmel taught briefly at the Brooklyn Museum Art School. Over the years she served as a visiting artist, critic, and lecturer at many colleges, and participated in numerous symposia, panel discussions and conferences. She has received several grants and awards including Macdowell Colony and Yaddo residencies.
Semmel has exhibited in the United States, Spain, the Netherlands, and South America. Her work is represented in the permanent collections of many museums including: Brooklyn Museum of Art, Chrysler Museum, Guild Hall, Museum of Women in the Arts, Parrish Art Museum, and Vassar College Museum.
While living in Spain, Semmel married José Antonio Nieto. The couple had two children and eventually divorced. Semmel later had long term relationships with novelist David Markson (1927-2010) and painter John Hardy (1923-2014). She continues to live and work in New York City and Easthampton, NY.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter Joan Semmel measure 5.9 linear feet and are dated 1949-2013, bulk circa 1960s-2013. The papers reflect her career and activities as a painter, writer, feminist and educator through biographical materials, correspondence, interviews, writings, project files, teaching files, printed material, and photographic materials.
Among the biographical materials are awards, educational records,and audiovisual recordings about Joan Semmel and her work.
Professional correspondence concerns exhibition arrangements, publication permissions, panel discussions, symposia, visiting artist and summer school appointments. Also included are letters of recommendation for colleagues and students. The majority of personal correspondence consists of letters from Semmel's lover, novelist David Markson. A few letters are from her husband, José Antonio Nieto. The remaining personal correspondence consists of letters from friends of a purely social nature, and routine business such as subletting her loft, jury duty, parking tickets, and real estate owned by a relative.
Audio visual recordings preserve two interviews with Joan Semmel; one was conducted for television broadcast, the other is unidentified.
Writings by Semmel include the manuscript, illustrations, research material, and letters relating to her unpublished book about women's erotic art. Also found are articles, artist's statements, and notes for talks about her work. The writings about Semmel consist of several student papers.
Project files relate to two exhibitions curated by Semmel and a project to document the status of women in art departments.
Most teaching files concern a course about contemporary women artists developed and taught by Semmel for the women's studies program at Rutgers University. Also documented are summer programs at Skowhegan and Sommerakademie in Austria where Semmel served as an instructor.
Printed material consists of exhibition catalogs, exhibition announcements, posters, articles, reviews, and miscellaneous items about or mentioning Semmel, often including reproductions of her work.
Photographs of people include Joan Semmel, friends and colleagues. Among the individuals pictured are: writer David Markson, painter John Hardy, her husband José Antonio Nieto; and feminist artists: Judy Bernstein, Mary Beth Edelson, Eunice Golden, Nancy Grossman, Harmony Hammond, Miriam Schapiro, Sylvia Sleigh, and May Stevens. There are slides, photographs, color photocopies and digital images of Semmel's paintings. Of particular interest are photographs, photocopies of photographs, and digital images that served as source material for paintings, including portrait commissions.
Bernstein, Judy; Edelson, Mary Beth; Golden, Eunice; Grossman, Nancy; Hammond, Harmony; Hardy, John; Markson, David; Nieto, José Antonio; Shapiro, Miriam, 1951-; Sleigh, Sylvia; Stevens, May; Art--Political aspects; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Educators--New York (State)--New York; Erotica; Feminism; Feminism and art; Illustrations; Interviews; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting, Abstract; Photographs; Video recordings; Women and erotica; Women artists
- Biographical Material, 1949-2013; Series 1; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes 6 videocassettes about Joan Semmel and her work. Awards and certificates are: Mencion de Honor, Salon de Marzo, 1967; Art Directors Club 58th Annual Exhibition 1979 Merit Award; NEA Visual Arts Fellowship Recipient Certificate, 1980; Citation presented by The Cooper Union, 1984; 71st Annual Guild Hall Members Exhibition honorable mention, 2009; The Cooper Union Alumni Association Golden Legion membership certificate, 2011; and WCA Lifetime Achievement Award with program and photographs, 2013. Educational records consist of high school, Cooper Union and Pratt Institute diplomas, and Pratt Institute transcripts. Financial records consist of a receipt for rent and utilities for an apartment in Buenos Aires and notes on the cost of plane tickets between Spain and the United States. Teaching credentials are a New York State provisional teaching certificate and New York City substitute license; a federal employment application for work as a substitute outlines her qualifications in detail.
  Arrangement note
  Files are alphabetized by folder title, and videocassettes about Joan Semmel and her work are arranged chronologically.
  - About Joan Semmel and Her Work (Box 1)
    - EyeTango Films/ARTifacts Television Pilot Segments, Demo, undated; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "What Follows…Joan Semmel", undated; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Joan Semmel Paints a Portrait," Paul Tschinkez, Art NY, CUNY TV, 1995; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Joan Semmel A Passion for Painting," ART/New York: A Video Series on Contemporary Art, Tape No. 42, 1995; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Not for Sale: Feminism and Art in the USA during the 1970s" by Laura Cottingham, Hawkeye Productions, 1998; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Address Book, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1967-2013 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Curricula Vitae, circa 1973-circa 2013 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Driver License; Passports, 1963-1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Educational Records – Certificate, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Educational Records – Diplomas, 1949-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Educational Records – Transcripts (1952-1970), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Financial Records, 1968; undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Teaching Credentials, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1973-2013; Series 2; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Professional correspondence concerns exhibitions, sales, loans, consignments, donations of artwork for fundraising, insurance, reproduction rights, publication permissions, panel discussions, symposia, visiting artist and summers school appointments. Also included are letters of recommendation written on behalf of colleagues and students.
  The majority of the personal correspondence consists of letters from Semmel's lover, novelist David Markson. Also included are photocopies of reviews and portions of Markson's published writings – some annotated or inscribed – a letter from his daughter, Johanna, paperback book covers from several of his novels, and the program from his memorial service. There are few letters from her husband, José Antonio Nieto. Other correspondence is with tenants who sublet Semmel's loft at various times, and the management company for her apartment. Letters to Semmel concern her will, estate planning, taxes, and real estate owned by a relative; also found are a few letters of a purely social nature from friends. Copies of letters sent by her are about jury duty, problems with her retirement account, a parking ticket and similar subjects. Also found is a color photocopy of a holiday card sent by Joan Semmel and partner John Hardy featuring Hardy's illustration of the two of them painting.
  Correspondence is arranged by year.
  - Professional Correspondence, 1973-1980; undated (Box 1, Folder 15-25)
  - Professional Correspondence, 1990-2013 (Box 2, Folder 1-22)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1984-2013; undated (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Personal Correspondence – David Markson, 1981-2010; undated (Box 2, Folder 25-28)
  - Personal Correspondence – José Antonio Nieto, 1974-2007; undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Interviews, circa 1970s-1986; Series 3; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  This series consists of audio visual recordings of two interviews with Joan Semmel. There are two copies of the interview conducted by Calvin Albert for his television show, "Art Beat." The interviewer and purpose of the other recording is unknown.
  - Joan Semmel, Edited, undated; 2 Videoreels (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Joan Semmel Interviewed by Calvin Albert, "Art Beat" #4, LTV, circa 1970s-1986; 1 Videocassettes (VHS); 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Writings, 1970s-2009; Series 4; 0.7 Linear feet Box 3
  Articles are "Women and Sexuality" written for Redbook but never published and the published version of "Sexual Imagery in Women's Art," written with April Kinglsey, that appeared in Women's Art Journal. Proposed titles for Semmel's unpublished book about women's erotic art changed over time and included "Sexual Imagery in Women's Art," "Erotic Art by Women," "Through the Object's Eye," "A New Eros," and "Imaging Eros."
  Among the writings about Semmel are "Feminist Theory as Applied to Through the Object's Eye Art Exhibit by Joan Semmel" by Toby Everett and "Sensuality, the Nude and the Dismantling of Sexist Imagery" a paper by Lisa A. Roberts presented at the Young Scholars Conference, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts and University of Virginia Commonwealth. Also included are student papers and a seminar presentation.
  Illustrations for Semmel's book arrived in two unlabeled binders and there is no internal evidence suggesting their order. The disbound volumes now bear the arbitrary tiles volumes A and volume B.
  - Writings by Semmel (Box 3)
    - Articles, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Book about Women's Erotic Art (Box 3)
      - Outline, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Manuscript, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
      - Illustrations, Volume A (dismantled), circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
      - Illustrations, Volume B (dismantled), circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
      - Contract, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Letters, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Letters from Agent and Publishers, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Submissions, circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Research Material, 1970s-2009 (Box 3, Folder 17-20)
    - Statements, 1980s-2006; undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Talks – Unidentified Venues, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Talks - Wexner Center, Ohio State University, 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Writings about Semmel, 1980-1995; undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Project Files, 1972-2000; Series 5; 3 Folders Box 3
  Project files document two exhibitions curated by Semmel. Also included are statistics documenting the status of women in art departments – as studio instructors, their representation in exhibitions, art history courses, slide libraries, etc. – with a letter from Semmel (representing the Ad Hoc Women's Committee of WEB, a national coalition of women in the arts) outlining goals and concerns.
  - Contemporary Women: Consciousness and Content (1977 October 1- November 7), The Brooklyn Museum of Art School (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Private Worlds (2000 May 31-July 8), Art in General, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Status of Women in Art Departments, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Teaching Files, 1970s-2000; Series 6; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  This series consists primarily of slides and a reading list for a course about contemporary women artists developed and taught by Semmel for the Rutgers University women's studies program, circa 1978. Also documented are programs at Skowhegan and Sommerakademie in Austria where Semmel served as an instructor for one summer at each school.
  - Contemporary Women Artists Course, Reading List, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Contemporary Women Artists Course, Slides (by artist, A-Z, unidentified), 1970s (Box 3, Folder 29-31)
  - Internationale Sommerakedemie für Bildende Kunst Salzburg, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Post-Tenure Review, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Recommendations, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Printed Material, circa 1960s-2013; Series 7; 2.2 Linear feet Boxes 4-6, OV 8
  All printed material mentions Semmel or includes reproductions of her work. Included are exhibition catalogs, announcements, articles, and reviews. Posters announce exhibitions, talks, summer sessions, and lectures. Miscellaneous printed items include advertisements for Semmel's exhibitions, press releases, newsletters, lecture announcements, notices of studio tours, and school catalogs.
  Five binders of printed material organized by record type were dismantled; now housed in folders, the contents of each binder retain the original order. Loose printed material, sorted by record type, is arranged by year.
  - Printed Material, Volumes 1-5 (Box 4)
    - Volume 1: Catalogues, etc., 1975-2013 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - Volume 2: Solo Exhibitions, 1975-2013 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Volume 3: Group Exhibitions, 1976-2012 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Volume 4: Reviews, undated; 1973-2004 (Box 4, Folder 11-13)
    - Volume 5: Reviews, 2002-2013 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
  - Articles/Reviews, undated; 1960s-2013 (Box 4, Folder 16-22)
  - Exhibition Announcements, undated; 1979-2013 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Catalogs – Group Shows, circa 1960s-2013 (Box 5, Folder 1-19)
  - Exhibition Catalogs – Solo Exhibitions, 1961-2013; undated (Box 5, Folder 20-22)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Items, 1960-1980; undated (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Posters, 1990-1992; undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Posters (from Box 6, Folder 3), 1990-1992; undated (Box OV 8)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1965-2013; Series 8; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  Photographs of people include portraits of Semmel, views of her in her studio, at home, and with others. Among the friends and colleagues pictured are: writer David Markson, painter John Hardy, her husband José Antonio Nieto; and feminist artists Judy Bernstein, Mary Beth Edelson, Eunice Golden, Nancy Grossman, Harmony Hammond, Miriam Schapiro, Sylvia Sleigh, and May Stevens. This series includes slides, photographs, and color photocopies of Semmel's paintings. Of particular interest are source materials consisting of color and black and white photographs, photocopies of photographs, and digital images used for paintings and commissioned portraits.
  This series is arranged by subject.
  - Joan Semmel, circa 1965-2015 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Joan Semmel with Friends, circa 1980s-2013; undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Paintings by Semmel, executed 1970s-2006 (35-mm color slides), undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Paintings by Semmel, executed 1978-1991 (dismantled binder; color photocopies), undated (Box 6, Folder 7-9)
  - Paintings by Semmel, executed 1970s-2000s, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Exhibition Installation, Unidentified Venue, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Installation, Lerner-Heller Gallery, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Source Material, undated (Box 7, Folder 7-11)
  - Source Material - Portrait Commissions, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)